Register of the Mont Pèlerin Society records
Hoover Institution Archives
Mont Pèlerin Society records
1938-2012
81123
Hoover Institution Archives
164 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 card file box, 10 envelopes (70.3 linear feet)
Correspondence, conference papers, programs, meeting materials, schedules, minutes, financial and membership records, essays, printed matter, sound recordings, and photographs relating to economic policy, laissez-faire, and liberty. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Mont Pèlerin Society.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of all sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access; digital copies also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org. To view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1981, with increments received in subsequent years.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Historical Note
International organization of laissez-faire economists.
Scope and Content Note
The first installment of the Mont Pèlerin Society records held at the Hoover Institution Archives was received in 1981 and described in a preliminary inventory that is now superseded by the present register.
Those initial records consisted mainly of Albert Hunold's correspondence, which now constitutes the bulk of the Correspondence series, and of his files relating to the general and regional meetings he organized as secretary of the society from 1948 to 1960, which are to be found in the Meetings File series and which also includes material relating to subsequent meetings up to 1990. It should be noted that the correspondence for the first meeting in 1947 also contains important letters dating back to 1945 regarding the founding of the Society.
The remainder of Albert Hunold's papers received in 1981 can be found in the Office File series, particularly the circulars and minutes of meetings. Also included are issues of The Mont Pèlerin Quarterly, edited by Hunold, and his 1962 writing "How the Mont Pèlerin Society Lost Its Soul," which gives his perspective on the so-called "Hunold Affair."
Later, in 1987, the Hoover Archives received the papers of several treasurers of the society, which can be found in the Treasurers' File series. Here too, the correspondence of these officers is particularly noteworthy, as is the correspondence with foundations, especially the Relm Foundation, regarding travel and other grants for members of the Society. Financial records and other materials relating to the meetings, however, were added to the Meetings File series.
The records in the smaller Newsletter File series, received in 1995, are also interesting, especially for the correspondence of Eric Brodin, one of the editors of The Mont Pèlerin Society Newsletter.
Finally, the collection includes a large amount of photographs, film strips, and sound tape reels, mostly relating to the Society's meetings.
Researchers interested in the activities of the society should also consult the Friedrich A. von Hayek papers at the Hoover Archives, particularly its series on the Mont Pèlerin Society in boxes 71-89, as well as the papers of several other prominent members such as John Davenport, Milton Friedman, Gottfried Haberler, F. A. Harper, Fritz Machlup, G. Warren Nutter, Karl Popper, and Gordon Tullock.
Also available for consultation in the reading room of the Hoover Archives is the excellent book by R. M. Hartwell, A History of the Mont Pèlerin Society (1995).
Additional records of the Mont Pèlerin Society were received by the archives in 2011 from Edwin J. Feulner, the treasurer of the Mont Pèlerin Society. The 2011 Incremental Materials series covers aspects of the Society's activities from 1974 to 2001, particularly meetings, membership, fellowships and awards. The papers are in roughly chronological order.
The 2013 Incremental Materials series covers the activities of the Mont Pèlerin Society from 1976 to 2012 and include institutional financial records, meetings, conference materials, membership information, the F. A. Hayek Essay Competition materials, various newsletters, and institutional correspondence.
Economic policy.; Free enterprise.; Liberty.; Economists.; Audiotapes.
- OFFICE FILE, 1945-1991 (Boxes 1-4)
  Scope and Contents note
  Booklets; circulars; minutes; printed matter, including writings by members of the society and issues of The Mont Pèlerin Quarterly (edited by Albert Hunold); programs of meetings; a subject file; and writings by Albert Hunold. Arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Booklets on the Society containing the Statement of Aims, Certificate and Articles of Incorporation, By-Laws, and List of Members, 1948, 1964, 1966 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Includes the General Not for Profit Corporation Act of 1959.
  - Circulars (of Friedrich A. von Hayek as President and of Albert Hunold as Secretary until September 1960; of Wilhelm Röpke as President and Albert Hunold as Vice-President, September 1960 - 1962)
    - General
      - 1947-1955 (Box-folder 1: 2)
      - 1956-1959 (Box-folder 1: 3)
      - 1960-1962 (Box-folder 1: 4)
        General note
        See also MEETINGS FILE/Kassel, Germany, 1960
        Includes Eva Röpke's circular of 21 December 1961, as well as minutes of the Council meeting in Kassel, September 7, 1960, and correspondence of Milton Friedman and Bruno Leoni.
    - Responses to Wilhelm Röpke's circular of December 6, 1961, and to Albert Hunold's circular of December 21, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1948-1961 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    Includes some agendas.
  - Printed matter
    - General
      - General, 1950-1986 (Box-folder 2: 1-3)
      - Clippings, 1945-1950 (Box-folder 2: 4-8)
        Includes clippings from the Neue Zürcher Zeitung, in particular obituaries for Walter Eucken and Harold Laski, articles on the Gotthardbund and by Albert Hunold on the "Genossenschaft" as "Ordnungsprinzip der Wirtschaft," as well as an article by Z. Giacometti.
      - Offprints and pamphlets (Box-folder 3: 1-4)
        Includes papers by members of the Mont Pèlerin Society, 1954-1991.
    - The Mont Pèlerin Quarterly (edited by Albert Hunold), 1959 April - 1962 January (Box-folder 3: 5-6)
  - Programs of the first eight meetings, 1947-1957 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Subject file
    - Adam Smith Institute, 1985 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - Foundation for Economic Education, 1951-1984 (Box-folder 4: 3-4)
    - Institut Économique de Paris, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 4: 5-6)
    - Ludwig von Mises Institute, 1978-1988 (Box-folder 4: 7-8)
    - Schweizerisches Institut für Auslandforschung, 1952-1966 (Box-folder 4: 9-10)
      See also CORRESPONDENCE
  - Writings by Albert Hunold
    - "Sternstunde der Mont Pèlerin Society,", undated (Box-folder 4: 11)
    - "The Mont Pèlerin Society,", 1955 Spring (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - "How the Mont Pèlerin Society Lost Its Soul,", 1962 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - "Kurzer Abriss über die Hintergründe des Zwistes in der Mont Pèlerin Society,", 1962 February 23 (Box-folder 4: 14)
- MEETINGS FILE, 1945-1990 (Boxes 5-28)
  Material related to general, regional, and directors' meetings organized by the society, including agendas, correspondence, lists of participants, memoranda, papers presented, programs, and miscellany related to the organization of the meetings. Arranged chronologically by date of meeting and alphabetically by physical form thereunder.
  - 1947, Mont Pèlerin, Switzerland (founding meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 5: 1)
      Includes Albert Hunold's circular of April 15 and William E. Rappard's response.
    - Clipping (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 5: 3)
        Consists mostly of correspondence to secure funding for the publication of a projected international monthly, funds which were subsequently used for the Mont Pèlerin meeting.
      - Organization, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 5: 4)
        Includes correspondence of Albert Hunold with Friedrich A. von Hayek, Wilhelm Röpke, William E. Rappard, Walter Eucken, F. Schnabel, Alexander Rüstow, and several other members. Also includes regrets and thank-you letters from participants.
      - Travel arrangements and hotel accommodations, 1947 February-March (Box-folder 5: 5)
        Includes participants' requests and correspondence of the proprietor of the Hôtel du Parc, with the stationery showing a photograph of the hotel above Vevey and Lake Geneva.
      - Excursions, 1947 February-April (Box-folder 5: 6)
        Includes correspondence with William E. Rappard.
      - Photograph albums of the meeting, 1947 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - Financial records, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - List of participants (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - Manuscripts brought by various participants (request of Friedrich A. von Hayek included) and circulated at the meeting, 1938-1945 (Box-folder 5: 10)
      Includes Wilhelm Röpke and Alexander Rüstow, "A Note on the Urgent Necessity of Re-Orientation of Social Science," Colloque Walter Lippmann, Institut International de Coopération Intellectuelle, Paris, France, August 1938; Albert Hunold, K. Brunner, and C. Mötteli, "Zur Frage der Gründung einer sozialwissenschaftlichen Studiengemeinschaft," Zurich, Switzerland, 8 December 1943; Friedrich A. von Hayek, "Historians and the Future of Europe," Cambridge, England, 28 February 1944; Wilhelm Röpke and Hans Zbinden, "Projekt einer internationalen Monatsschrift, Geneva and Bern, April 1945; Wilhelm Röpke, "Plan for an International Periodical," Geneva, Switzerland, August 1945. Also includes an undated manuscript by Wilhelm Röpke, "Some Notes on the German Problem," Geneva, Switzerland.
    - Memorandum of association (Box-folder 5: 11)
      Includes handwritten draft by Friedrich A. von Hayek.
    - Minutes of proceedings (Box-folder 5: 12-13)
      Includes address by Friedrich A. von Hayek on the aims and organization of the meeting.
    - Notes, mostly by Albert Hunold (Box-folder 5: 14)
    - Report on the conference (Box-folder 5: 15)
    - Statement of aims (Box-folder 5: 16)
      Includes handwritten notes by Friedrich A. von Hayek.
  - 1948, Basel, Switzerland (European directors' meeting) (Box-folder 6: 1)
    Minutes and Albert Hunold's notes and correspondence, 1948-1949.
  - 1949, Seelisberg, Switzerland (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 6: 2)
      Includes correspondence and Friedrich A. von Hayek's report on the conference.
    - Clipping (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - Financial records (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - Notes by Albert Hunold (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - 1950, Bloemendaal, Netherlands (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 6: 7)
    - Booklets, including a commemorative one by Ludwig von Mises, with photographs of participants (Box-folder 6: 8)
    - Clipping (Box-folder 6: 9)
    - Notes by Albert Hunold (Box-folder 6: 10)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 6: 11-12)
  - 1951, Beauvallon, France (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 7: 1)
      Includes bibliography of publications by members.
    - Clipping (Box-folder 7: 2)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 7: 3-4)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 7: 5-6)
  - 1953, Seelisberg, Switzerland (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 7: 7)
      Includes circulars by Friedrich A. von Hayek and report by Albert Hunold, as well as a bibliography of publications by members and "post-Seelisberg" poetry by Volkmar Muthesius.
    - Clippings (Box-folder 7: 8)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 7: 9)
    - Financial records (Box-folder 7: 10)
    - Minutes of the Council and general meetings, 1953 September 11 (Box-folder 7: 11)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - 1954, Venice, Italy (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 8: 1)
      Includes correspondence, circulars, and report by Friedrich A. von Hayek.
    - Clippings (Box-folder 8: 2)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 8: 3-6)
    - Financial records (Box-folder 8: 7)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 8: 8-10)
  - 1956, Berlin, Germany (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 9: 1-2)
      Includes report by Friedrich A. von Hayek, and circulars and correspondence by Albert Hunold.
    - Clippings (Box-folder 9: 3)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 9: 4)
    - Notes by Albert Hunold (Box-folder 9: 5)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 9: 6)
      Includes some correspondence.
    - Printed matter (Box-folder 9: 7)
    - Transcript of tape recording (Box-folder 9: 8)
    - Transcript of tape recording (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
  - 1957, St. Moritz, Switzerland (general, 10th anniversary, meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 10: 3)
      Includes circulars and report on the conference by Friedrich A. von Hayek, and ninth annual fiscal report.
    - Addresses by Friedrich A. von Hayek and Albert Hunold (Box-folder 10: 4)
    - Clippings (Box-folder 10: 5)
    - Correspondence
      - General - Kemp, Arthur (Box-folder 10: 6)
      - Business (Box-folder 10: 7-8)
    - Financial records
      - General (Box-folder 10: 9-10)
      - Donations (Box-folder 10: 11)
      - Donations (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Papers presented
      - General (Box-folder 11: 2-4)
      - Hayek, Friedrich A. von (Box-folder 11: 5)
    - Printed matter (Box-folder 11: 6)
  - 1958, Princeton, New Jersey (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 11: 7)
      Includes circulars by Albert Hunold and report on the conference by Friedrich A. von Hayek, as well as a proclamation of September 10, 1958.
    - Clippings, including on Albert Hunold's talks in Mexico and Guatemala, 1958 September-October (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 12: 2-4)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 12: 5-6)
    - Transcript of tape recording (Box-folder 12: 7)
    - Transcript of tape recording (Box-folder 13: 1-2)
  - 1959, Oxford, England (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 13: 3)
      Includes notes by Albert Hunold.
    - Clippings (Box-folder 13: 4)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 13: 5-7)
      Includes correspondence with John Jewkes and others dating back to 1952.
    - Minutes of the Council meetings, September 8 and 10, and of the general meeting, September 10, 1959 (Box-folder 13: 8)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 13: 9)
    - Transcript of tape recording (Box-folder 13: 10)
  - 1960, Kassel, Germany (general meeting).
    See also OFFICE FILE/Circulars
    - General (Box-folder 14: 1-2)
    - Circulars of Fritz Machlup and George Stigler (June 1); Albert Hunold, Wilhelm Röpke, Franz Böhm, and Louis Baudin (July 18); Albert Hunold (July 18 and 21); Friedrich A. von Hayek (August 3 and 13); Wilhelm Röpke (August 18) (Box-folder 14: 3)
      Includes related correspondence of several of the above, as well as of Milton Friedman and Bruno Leoni, 1959-1961.
    - Clippings (Box-folder 14: 4)
      Includes an article by Albert Hunold, "Die Kasseler Tagung der Mont Pèlerin Society," November 1960.
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 14: 5-8)
    - Financial records (Box-folder 14: 9)
    - Financial records (Box-folder 15: 1-3)
    - Minutes of Council meeting, 1960 September 7 (Box-folder 15: 4)
      Includes testimony of Lena Schwendener.
    - Notes by Albert Hunold (Box-folder 15: 5)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 15: 6-8)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 16: 1)
    - Proxies received by George Stigler (Box-folder 16: 2)
    - Report by Wilhelm Röpke entitled "Report on What Has Been Happening since the Kassel Meeting and the Settlement Concluded There" (Box-folder 16: 3)
    - Transcript of tape recording (Box-folder 16: 4-9)
  - 1961, Turin, Italy (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 16: 10)
    - Clippings (Box-folder 16: 11)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 16: 12)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 17: 1)
  - 1962, Knokke, Belgium (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 17: 2)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 17: 3-5)
  - 1965, Stresa, Italy (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 17: 6)
      Includes circulars and correspondence.
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors' meeting, 1965 September 3 (Box-folder 17: 7)
      Includes ideas presented by Mr. Kiuchi at the September 6 meeting, as well as Bruno Leoni's report and Clarence Philbrook's draft letter to Leoni.
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 17: 8)
  - 1966, Tokyo, Japan (regional meeting) (Box-folder 17: 9)
    Papers presented
  - 1967, Vichy, France (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 17: 10)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 17: 11)
    - Financial records (Box-folder 17: 12)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 17: 13)
  - 1968, Aviemore, Scotland (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 18: 1)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 18: 2)
  - 1970, Munich, Germany (general meeting) (Box-folder 18: 3)
    Includes notes on the meeting by H. F. Langenberg and list of members delinquent with their dues.
  - 1971, Rockford, Illinois (regional meeting) (Box-folder 18: 4)
    Includes correspondence of Arthur Kemp.
  - 1971, Montreux, Switzerland (special board meeting) (Box-folder 18: 5)
    Includes circulars, correspondence, reports, and summaries.
  - 1972, Montreux, Switzerland (general, 25th anniversary meeting) (Box-folder 18: 6)
    Includes correspondence and memoranda.
  - 1973, Guatemala City, Guatemala (regional meeting) (Box-folder 18: 7)
    Includes correspondence.
  - 1974, Brussels, Belgium (general meeting) (Box-folder 18: 8)
    Includes agenda for board meeting, correspondence, and an article by Alan Reynolds.
  - 1975, Hillsdale, Michigan (regional meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 18: 9)
      Includes a summary of history and aims of the Society.
    - Clippings (Box-folder 18: 10)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 18: 11)
  - 1976, St. Andrews, Scotland (general meeting) (Box-folder 19: 1)
  - 1977, Paris, France (regional meeting) (Box-folder 19: 2)
    Papers presented, published under the title Le Libéralisme? De Karl Marx à Milton Friedman.
  - 1977, Amsterdam, Netherlands (regional meeting) (Box-folder 19: 3)
    Circular
  - 1978, Hong Kong (general meeting)
    Includes material relating to the ad-hoc meeting in Taipei, Taiwan, August 30 - September 2.
    - General (Box-folder 19: 4-7)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 20: 1-10)
      Includes a letter from Friedrich A. von Hayek.
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 21: 1-7)
    - Financial records (Box-folder 21: 8)
    - Registration forms (Box-folder 21: 9-10)
    - Regrets (Box-folder 22: 1)
  - 1979, Madrid, Spain (regional meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 22: 2)
      Includes notes re Friedrich A. von Hayek and Max Thurn's memoranda regarding meetings on September 3 and 6.
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 22: 3)
    - Financial records (Box-folder 22: 4)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 22: 5-7)
  - 1980, Stanford, California (general meeting held at the Hoover Institution)
    - General (Box-folder 22: 8)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 23: 1-5)
    - Financial records (Box-folder 23: 6)
    - Minutes of board meetings of September 8, 9, and 11, 1980 (Box-folder 23: 7)
    - Papers presented, including opening speech of Manuel Ayau (Box-folder 23: 8)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 24: 1)
  - 1981, Viña del Mar, Chile (regional meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 24: 2)
      Includes report on the meeting by Eric Brodin.
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 24: 3)
    - Papers presented, including opening speech by Pedro Ibañez O. (Box-folder 24: 4-6)
  - 1981, Stockholm, Sweden (regional meeting) (Box-folder 25: 1)
    Includes correspondence and registration forms.
  - 1982, Berlin, Germany (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 25: 2)
      Includes correspondence and clippings.
    - Papers presented, including Chiaki Nishiyama's opening address (Box-folder 25: 3)
  - 1983, Vancouver, Canada (regional meeting) (Box-folder 25: 4)
    Includes correspondence and clipping.
  - 1984, Paris, France (regional meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 25: 5)
    - Papers presented, including Jacques Chirac's speech honoring Friedrich A. von Hayek, and Hayek's closing address (Box-folder 25: 6-7)
  - 1984, Cambridge, England (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 25: 8)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 25: 9-10)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 26: 1)
  - 1985, Sydney, Australia (regional meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 26: 2)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 26: 3-5)
  - 1986, St. Vincent, Italy (general meeting) (Box-folder 26: 6-7)
    Papers presented, including James Buchanan's opening address.
  - 1987, Indianapolis, Indiana (regional meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 27: 1)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 27: 2)
  - 1988, Tokyo-Kyoto, Japan (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 27: 3)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 27: 4-6)
  - 1988, Taipei, Taiwan (special meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 27: 7)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 27: 8)
  - 1990, Munich, Germany (general meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 28: 1)
    - Papers presented (Box-folder 28: 2-4)
  - 1990, Antigua, Guatemala (regional meeting)
    - General (Box-folder 28: 5)
    - Papers presented, including Manuel Ayau's opening address (Box-folder 28: 6)
  - Miscellaneous papers presented at unidentified meetings (Box-folder 28: 7)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1946-1978 (Boxes 29-44)
  Correspondence of three secretaries of the society, mostly of Albert Hunold (including correspondence after he had left the Society), arranged chronologically by name of officer. Also includes correspondence of John Jewkes, president of the Society from 1962 to 1964.
  - Hunold, Albert (Secretary, 1948-1960; Vice-President, 1960-1962)
    - 1946-1948
      - General
        - A-D (Box-folder 29: 1)
        - E-G (Box-folder 29: 2)
        - H (Box-folder 29: 3)
        - I-P (Box-folder 29: 4)
        - R-W (Box-folder 29: 5)
      - Economics conference organized by Albert Hunold and Alfred Amonn, Einsiedeln, Switzerland, July 26-28 (Box-folder 29: 6)
    - 1947-1949 (Box-folder 29: 7-8)
      Correspondence with the Organisation for European Economic Co-Operation, the Economic Cooperation Administration, and many others, including Friedrich A. von Hayek and Walter Eucken.
    - 1949
      - January-June
        - A-C (Box-folder 29: 9)
        - D-G (Box-folder 29: 10)
        - H-L (Box-folder 29: 11)
        - M-S (Box-folder 30: 1)
        - T-Z (Box-folder 30: 2)
      - July-December
        - A-D (Box-folder 30: 3)
        - E-K (Box-folder 30: 4)
        - L-S (Box-folder 30: 5)
        - T-Z (Box-folder 30: 6)
    - 1949-1951 - Jodlerklub "Echo vom Rigi" (Box-folder 30: 7)
    - 1950
      - General
        - January-June
          - A-C (Box-folder 30: 8)
          - D-E (Box-folder 30: 9)
          - G (Box-folder 30: 10)
          - H-I (Box-folder 30: 11)
          - K-L (Box-folder 31: 1)
          - M-P (Box-folder 31: 2)
          - R-Z (Box-folder 31: 3)
        - July-December
          - A-B (Box-folder 31: 4)
          - C-E (Box-folder 31: 5)
          - F-H (Box-folder 31: 6)
          - I-K (Box-folder 31: 7)
          - L-M (Box-folder 31: 8)
          - N-R (Box-folder 31: 9)
          - S-W (Box-folder 31: 10)